<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of the true church In a sermon preach'd at the French church in the Savoy, upon these words, How goodly are they tents, O Jacob, and thy tabernacles, O Israel, Numb. XXIV. v. 5. By A. D'Astor de Laussac, formerly a prior and an archdeacon of the church of Rome.</title>
            <author>Dastor de Laussac, Antoine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L623C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832954</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2188:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of the true church In a sermon preach'd at the French church in the Savoy, upon these words, How goodly are they tents, O Jacob, and thy tabernacles, O Israel, Numb. XXIV. v. 5. By A. D'Astor de Laussac, formerly a prior and an archdeacon of the church of Rome.</title>
                  <author>Dastor de Laussac, Antoine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Matt. Wotton, at the Three Daggers in Fleetstreet, aud [sic] sold by A. Baldwin in Warwick-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy cropped with loss of text; lacks pp. 26-27?</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lambeth Palace Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Numbers XXIV, 5 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37429:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Character of the True Church. IN A SERMON Preach'd at the French Church in the Savoy, Upon theſe Words, How goodly are thy Tents, O Jacob, and thy Tabernacles, O Iſrael, Numb. XXIV. v. 5. By A. D'Aſtor de Lauſſac, formerly a Prior and an Archdeacon of the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Matt. Wotton, at the Three Daggers in Fleetſtreet, and ſold by A. Baldwin in Warwick-lame. 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37429:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37429:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Perſon who is deeply touch'd with the miſeries which poor <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants ſuffer while there, and more rigorouſly for but attempting to get away (tho with the loſs of their Eſtates) was mightily pleas'd to find, by reading the Original of this diſcourſe, that a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt of their Nation had been ſo far from acting in thoſe Cruelties, that he had quitted his Preferments, to become of himſelf a Refugee, being forc'd only by the power of Truth to yield at laſt to the Conviction of his Conſcience (which he owns he had long reſiſted) and that in their chiefeſt Church, the <hi>Savoy,</hi> he had made a free and open Abjuration of all the errors of Popery, giving very many weighty Reaſons whereby he was mov'd to Renounce it; which, utter'd with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern by ſuch a New Convert, cou'd not but draw great attention, and thereby (as alſo by his example) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to work that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Faith, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and confirm in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37429:3"/>
            <p>An earneſt deſire; and hope of good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by thoſe motives, if more known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, made the ſaid Perſon wiſh they were in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This the Author hearing, got the Sermon Tranſlated, and brought it to him, by whoſe encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he has now Printed it. for a ſecond and more publick Abjuring of all Popiſh Superſtitions, with the methods ſtill us'd in <hi>France,</hi> (and now more ſeverely than ever) to make Proſelytes by Perſecution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> (not many years ago) was in manifeſt danger of the like, and ſeveral large ſteps had haſtily been made here to that end; but the King of Kings ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly overturn'd that confidence, when at the higheſt, and by his mighty hand, the Religion of this Church, and the Laws of this Kingdom, were ſtrangely reſcu'd from the violence of Arbitrary Power, and are now peaceably re-eſtabliſhed; which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing mercies ſhou'd by this Nation with moſt hearty thankfulneſs be for ever remembred, to the Glory of God, and Honour of the King, his Inſtrument in that Wonderful Revolution.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37429:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>NUMB. XXIV. 5.</hi> How goodly are thy Tents, O Jacob, and thy Tabernacles, O Iſrael.</head>
            <p>THeſe words ſpoke <hi>Balaam,</hi> and bleſs'd <hi>Iſrael,</hi> not ſo much in reference to any greatneſs or magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence he ſaw in that people, as by reaſon of ſome extraordinary and miraculous influence he felt within himſelf. This falſe Prophet, drawn away by the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own heart, which God ſuffer'd him to be led by, follow'd the ſecond Meſſengers of the King of <hi>Moab;</hi> and tho he appear'd ſenſible of his fault, when frighten'd by the Angel of the Lord, yet all his ways, and all the ſubtle contrivances of his hypocriſie eaſily perſwade us, that in order to proſecute the preſſing inſtances of <hi>Balak,</hi> and ſatisfie his own deſire, his real intention was to curſe <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But no ſooner does he think himſelf at liberty again, and juſt ready to execute his pernicious deſign, but he feels within himſelf an inward power that ſtops him, a ſecret and incomprehenſible motion, which in an inſtant turns his heart in the behalf of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and forces him to cry out in ſpite of <hi>Balak,</hi> nay, and in ſpite of himſelf, <hi>How goodly are thy Tents, O Jacob, and thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt but you are beforehand with me in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this accident to my preſent circumſtance. You have here before you a Miniſter of error and falſhood, who comes to joyn with you in the profeſſion of a truth he has but too long withſtood. One, who though engaged by his Birth, Education and Miniſtry, to perſecute your holy Religion, yet is now thoroughly convinc'd of his paſt blindneſs, ready to turn into bleſſings the curſes he formerly pronounc'd againſt you. How ſhou'd I curſe, whom God has not curs'd!</p>
            <p>'Tis not expected I ſhou'd pretend any way to extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate or leſſen my errors and miſtakes. I have, I own it to my ſhame and confuſion, I have for many years ſtifled
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37429:4"/>the ſaving impulſes of Grace; and at the very time it pleas'd Almighty God to enlighten me in his ways, and to open my eyes to the purity of the Evangelical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; I did but too long defer my converſion, and was at a ſtand between God and the World. God alone, from whom nothing can be hid, knows what ſtruggles and agonies I underwent. But at laſt his efficacious Grace triumph'd over the hardneſs of my heart. He drew me over to him by the ties of meekneſs and gentleneſs. I am the leaſt of Chriſts Diſciples, unworthy to be call'd a Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſince I perſecuted the Church of God: but by the grace of God, I am what I am. Clouds of error and ignorance, ſentiments of fleſh and blood, prejudices of birth and education, groundleſs ſhame, which force ſo many to with-hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs, all your illuſions are now diſſipated, you have given way to the bright and ſhining light of the Goſpel, which alone is able to enlighten our minds, and to that victorious grace, that can in a moment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all our ill habits, and change the affections of our hearts. Since then it has pleas'd God in his infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, to open my eyes, and looſe my tongue, ſince it has pleas'd him to put theſe words in my mouth, why ſhou'd not I cry out with <hi>Balaam, How goodly are thy tents, O Jacob, and thy tabernacles, O Iſrael!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The following diſcourſe being more particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for your edification than inſtruction, I ſhall paſs by the different acceptations theſe words may admit of. I thought it therefore moſt proper to gather from thence the principal motives that prompted me to embrace the doctrine of the Reformed Churches, by ſhewing that therein I find the diſtinguiſhing characters of the true Church of Chriſt. I diſcover in your Communion the Church of Chriſt, becauſe 'tis the authority of the word of God that has preſerv'd in it the purity of the Faith. This is the firſt character; the ſecond is, that the purity of the Faith draws upon it the perſecutions which the world doth exerciſe againſt it.</p>
            <p>'Tis the Church of Chriſt, ſince it goes by no other rule than that of his Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37429:4"/>
            <p>'Tis the Church of Chriſt, ſince it ſuffers perſecution for his name, and for his truth. Theſe ſhall be the two heads of the diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian World is particularly divided into two different Communions: they agree in many effential points of Religion, but differ in the principle that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned their ſeparation, and gives each of them a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Character. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> uſes the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to attribute a ſupream Authority to its Miniſtry, which makes it head not only to be as the oracle of God, but the ſole Interpreter of the truths therein contain'd, and the infallible judge of controverſies on that occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Religion that proteſts againſt the authority which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Miniſtry has aſſum'd over the Scripture, looks upon the Word of God as the only rule of the Chriſtian Faith, and gives the Scripture ſo great an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the Miniſtry, that Chriſtianity is no longer liable to its deciſions, than as they are conformable to Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>The authority which this Supream Miniſter has aſſum'd over the world of God, has by degrees alter'd the purity of the Faith, by adding to, or taking from what Chriſt had eſtabliſh'd; whereas the authority which the word of God has re-aſſum'd over the Miniſtry, has re-eſtabliſh'd the purity of that Faith which Chriſtianity enjoy'd in the golden days of the Church. Hence ariſes the diverſity of Communions, one of which pulls up out of the field of the Lord what the other had ſown: from this oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition proceeded the animoſities of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt the Proteſtants. But Chriſt has taken care to comfort his Church in this diſtreſs it labours under, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it withal, that he had been hated firſt: Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is for no other reaſon odious, but becauſe it roots up thoſe plants our Heavenly Father had not planted, and pulls down from the heavenly edifice what had been built with wood, hay, and ſtubble.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If the Miniſtry, uſing the authority aſſum'd, had only ſet up ſome new curious doctrine interwoven with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man opinions, I own it won'd have been hard for the purity of ſaith to have born with it; but yet rather than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37429:5"/>break unity it wou'd have been neceſſary to have waited till the Lord had try'd every mans work,<note place="margin">Ibid. v. 13</note> as St <hi>Paul</hi> has expreſt it.</p>
            <p>But no leſs than the Church it ſelf was aim'd at. No other foundation, ſays St <hi>Paul,</hi> can any man lay but that which has been laid, <hi>viz.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt: 'Tis not only the death of Chriſt, his reſurrection, his aſcenſion, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the right hand of God, that are the foundation of the Church; all theſe myſteries wou'd have been needleſs, had they been unknown; and they had been unknown, that not God ſpoke by his Prophets, by Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles. Now the word of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are ſet forth all theſe myſteries, has been the ſeed of the Faith, and Faith having ſubjected Reaſon to its au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, has been the foundation of the Church. And this is its character ſet forth by Chriſt himſelf, when he ſaid,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever hears my ſayings, and doth them; I will liken him to a wiſe man, who built his houſe upon a rock;</hi> whereas he that hears and doth them not,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be like a fooliſh man who built his houſe upon the ſand.</hi> Whence it clearly appears, that the true and only foundation of Chriſtian Religion, was the ſubjecting of human under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the word of God.</p>
            <p>Now to eſtabliſh a Church meerly upon the authority of a Miniſtry, that ſets us for a rule of Faith, what is rather grounded upon tradition, than upon revelation, is building a houſe upon the ſand, becauſe 'tis no more than to hear the word of God, and not to be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to its anthority, to lay another foundation than what has been laid. 'Twas then neceſſary to find out another principle, to return to the original foundation of the Church, that is, to look upon Holy Writ, as the only rule of Faith, and the only foundation of the authority of that Miniſtry Chriſtians are to be led by.</p>
            <p>Nay, it ſeems evident, that Faith coming from hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hearing from the Word, there is ſo great an affinity between the word of God and Faith, that the faithful's ſubmiſſion to the authority of the Scripture is one of thoſe truths, which Reaſon and Revelation do not more clearly prove than every Chriſtians natural
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37429:5"/>ſuggeſtion. The being of a God is a truth reſulting from a natural inſtinct. 'Tis a natural inſtinct in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity that there is a Church; and in that Church, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally taken, 'tis a natural notion that the faithful muſt be rul'd by the word of God. What occaſion'd that numberleſs train of falſe Gods among the Pagans, but that natural notion man always carried along with him, of ſome true Divinity, from whom he deriv'd his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, life, and motion? Whence comes it in Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that all Hereticks have been ſeen to give their Sect the name of a Church, but becauſe there never was any Chriſtian that own'd Chriſt for the Saviour of the world, but was ſenſible there was a Church, wherein the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful might attain Salvation? and why was there never any Heretick in all theſe ſuppos'd Churches, but what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to authorize his opinions by the Scripture? This is ſuch a natural notion, as cannot but convince any reaſonable mind, that Chriſtians muſt have the word of God for the rule of their faith, ſince by that ſame word they have faith convey'd to them: And if in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, Hypocriſie is a homage Vice pays to Virtue, it may be ſaid in Religion, that that affectation in Hereticks of being grounded upon the Scripture, is an homage Error pays to the Truth, whoſe original ſource, and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble witneſs is in that Holy Word, it being to the Church of Chriſt, what the mercy-ſeat, whence were pronounc'd the oracles of God, was to <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. How cou'd we judge better of the Church of Chriſt, than by the model himſelf has left us, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>and upon this rock will I build my Church;</hi> he does not ſay upon thee, <hi>Peter,</hi> but upon the rock, that is, upon that Chriſt <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> had but juſt confeſs'd, becauſe the Church cou'd neither be founded upon the perſon nor upon the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of St <hi>Peter,</hi> but upon the confeſſion that Apoſtle had made of Chriſt, who is the fundamental Stone of the Spiritual Building; Chriſt does not ſay here, thou ſhalt build my Church, for man is not able to build the Church of God, but I will build my Church, becauſe the character that diſtinguiſhes the Church of Chriſt from all ſuch as might uſurp that name, is, that Chriſt is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37429:6"/>foundation of it, and the Maſter-builder; in this Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Edifice no other hand muſt be ſeen but that of Chriſt, that is, his will, his power, his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the authority of his word. And tho St <hi>Peter,</hi> and the other Diſciples have been aſſociated to that great work, yet 'tis Chriſt's hand alone that has wrought all by them. They indeed preach'd, but Chriſt converted; they wrought Miracles, but 'twas through his name; they baptiz'd, but Chriſt perform'd the regeneration; in a word, 'twas Chriſt edify'd his Church. <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Jacob!</hi> This is certainly the character of Chriſt's Church, ſince it receives no other truth but that he brought upon earth, no other ſolemnities but thoſe he conſecrated, no other Sacraments but thoſe he conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, no other expiatory Sacrifice but that of his death, nor any other merit but that of his blood. This is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Church of Chriſt, ſince all is founded upon his word, all is edify'd by his doctrine, all is referr'd to his glory.</p>
            <p>'Tis not ſo with the Church which Papal authority has ſet up, which would needs force Chriſtianity to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it as the Church of Chriſt. How many rules of faith! how many acts of piety, which have no ſolid founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Holy Writ! That's a building wherein Chriſt's hand appears much leſs than thoſe of the builders, ſince in it the authority of the Scripture gives way to that of the Miniſtry, as if that were become the original ſource of Divine Revelation.</p>
            <p>One wou'd think our Saviour, who knew all things, had a mind to prevent the errors whereinto men were like to fall, by taking a Church of men's ſetting up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly upon Earth in the name of Chriſt, for that which he had founded himſelf in the fulneſs of time; and indeed he does prevent it by the precautions he takes in the eſtabliſhment of the Apoſtolical Miniſtry, which he aſſociates to the building of his Church. He chooſes for Apoſtles, men of the loweſt rank of the people, ignorant, unlearned, ſelf-intereſted, fearful, in a word, men who were no way proportionate to the work they were deſign'd for. Why did he leave them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37429:6"/>in this ſtate of infirmity, till the coming down of the Holy Ghoſt, but that the tryal of their weakneſs might make them ſenſible, 'twas Jeſus Chriſt, who acted in them at the very time they were building up his Church, that ſo they might not arrogate to themſelves the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of it, tho their hands were employ'd in the Structure? Why was our Saviour pleaſed to particularize the failings and infirmities of his Apoſtles, but as a precaution to poſterity, which might have attributed to them the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of having edifyed his Church. His wiſdom having diſcover'd to them their natural inſufficiency, leaves no room in them for preſumption; by ſhewing them they had no vertue but what came from above: it characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizes the Church of God, by Chriſt's hand alone that built it.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant how that the Evangelical Miniſtry muſt laſt to the end of the world; how Chriſt promis'd his Apoſtles he wou'd be always with them; and how this promiſe is to be fulfill'd in the Succeſſion of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. But divine wiſdom uſes the ſame caution in the ſucceſſion as in the eſtabliſhment thereof. What cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter does he give to the ſucceſſion of the Miniſtry? no other than the ſucceſſion of his doctrine; I ſend you, as my Father has ſent me, <hi>Go and teach all nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28</note> 
               <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you, and lo I am with you always, even unto the end of the World.</hi> Theſe laſt words include a promiſe made to the Miniſtry, and a condition impoſed in order to partake of the promiſe, teaching them, as I have commanded you, that's the condition on which he promiſes to be with them. They are ſent by Chriſt, as Chriſt was by the Father. Chriſt ſent by his Heavenly Father, makes the truth of his miſſion appear by the tranſcendency of his miracles, which are ſo many proofs of his Divinity, by the apparition of the Holy Ghoſt, that declares him to men for the beloved Son of God. But he does not impoſe the neceſſity of believing his Doctrine, otherwiſe than as it is conformable to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſent him. Whence proceeds this admirable conduct? But from this reaſon, that the Evangelical
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37429:7"/>Miniſtry was to be excercis'd by men; the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt were to longer to accompany the Miniſtry, than was requiſite to eſtabliſh the Faith; after that, the Church was to be directed by the Holy Ghoſt. Jeſus Chriſt was to be with the Miniſtry, but after an inviſible manner. If the viſible ſucceſſion of the Miniſtry had been a ſufficient proof of its miſſion, then ſome hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite or other, ſitting in the Apoſtolical Chair, might have pretended to have acted by the ſpirit of God, when there was no ſuch thing. The faithful might have been impos'd upon, unleſs Chriſt had promis'd his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to be with them, ſetting them this Law withal, to teach as he had commanded them, and unleſs he had charactariz'd the miniſtry by the ſucceſſion of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſo that every miniſtry that teaches not what the Apoſtles have taught, or that ſets for a rule of ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing than they taught, is not look'd upon as the Apoſtolical Miniſtry. Boaſt he never ſo much of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſucceeded St. <hi>Peter,</hi> unleſs he have the ſucceſſion of the Doctrine, he has no right to it, he muſt not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The truth Chriſtian Religion obliges us to believe came to us from the Father by the Son, from the Son of God by the Holy Ghoſt, from the Holy Ghoſt by the Apoſtles by their Succeſſors. Now, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be the true Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, is but to examine whether the truth they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, the Religion they propoſe, flow from the primitive Spring. <hi>How goodly are the tents, O Jacob!</hi> How great muſt our happineſs be, who live in the boſom of a Church, which holds it for an axiom of faith to be conformable to God's Holy Word, which is ſo happy as to be directed by a Miniſtry, that may without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy ſay, the Religion we preach comes not from our ſelves, we are not the Authors of it, 'tis the very ſame the Apoſtles left us in the Goſpel, the Apoſtles receiv'd from the Holy Ghoſt, the Holy Ghoſt deriv'd it from the boſom of the word incarnate, the word incarnate from the boſom of the Heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>Thus by the Authority of the word of God, is the ſucceſſion and purity of Faith preſerv'd in the Chriſtian
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37429:7"/>World. Such is the neceſſity of this grand principle, that no ſooner came the Church to forget it but it fell into a moſt deplorable condition. Look back into thoſe all at once happy, and unhappy days, when Peace ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding that perſecution which the Church had ſo long groan'd under, corrupted Chriſtianity, which all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of Hereticks and cruelty of Tyrants were not able to oppreſs. The Church became great in wealth and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but at the ſame time ſmall in virtue; the ſalt of the earth vaniſht away, all fell into corruption. Both Paſtors and Flock had much at the ſame time a general diſguſt for heavenly things; the ſacred fire of the Altar went out by degrees, whilſt no other burnt thereon, but that of Luſt and Ambition: The Children of <hi>Eli</hi> made it their main buſineſs to encreaſe the rights and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Prieſthood; the Church, of a Heavenly Kingdom became a Temporal Reign; the Apoſtolical Chair became a Throne, whereon the Apoſtles Succeſſors were not aſhamed to exact thoſe Divine Honours the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves had rejected; and the Holy Scripture, the authority whereof had till then govern'd the Church, became itſelf Captive to the ambition of the Miniſtry; it violated its natural ſenſe, and ſo forc'd it to be eſtabliſh an authority till then unknown.</p>
            <p>When faith was in its purity, the Scripture lodg'd the keys of the Kingdom of Heaven in the Hands of the whole Apoſtolical Colledge, in whoſe name St <hi>Peter</hi> had anſwer'd Jeſus Chriſt. But when the faith was once corrupted, then the Scripture was forc'd to allow none but <hi>Peter</hi> to be intruſted with them, and ſuch as flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd themſelves to be his ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>When faith was in its purity, the Scripture deliver'd up the keys of the Kingdom of Heaven as a patent whereby they were impower'd to the preach the Goſpel, by which the gates of Heaven were open to believers, and ſhut to unbelievers. But when the ſame faith was once corrupted, then the Scripture was made to ſignify by thoſe keys, the power not only of preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but even of interpreting it after an infallible man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and of filling up with their traditions what was deficient.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37429:8"/>
            <p>When faith was in its purity, this power of binding and looſing was receiv'd by the Apoſtles, as a lawful power to explain in Religion what was legal or illegal, what good, or what ill. But after the Corruption of the faith, this power of binding and looſing erected a tribunal, where Chriſt's pretended Miniſters inveſting themſelves with the Power of remitting ſins, which is an eſſential attribute of God, loos'd ſinners by their Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, or bound them by the refuſal of the ſame. Nay, this power had different degrees of juriſdiction according to the different miniſters in whom it was lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; and being conſider'd as in its center, there was a tribunal ſet up, whence proceeded Indulgences, and Excommunications, which bound Chriſtians according as they were ſubject or rebellious to this new authority.</p>
            <p>This authority, this Supream degree of ſpiritual juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, was none indeed of thoſe truths Chriſtianity moſt depended upon, but it ſo much favour'd the ſpirit of ambition and power, that laying aſide the thoughts of Chriſt's having condemn'd it in the Apoſtolical Colledge, they were eaſily ſeduc'd by this fair outſide. What en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours were us'd, in order to back with arguments from the Scripture, the authority of the Miniſtry that was juſt ſet up? But methinks this was placing the Ark before <hi>Dagon</hi>'s Idol, which fell before it. This autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in judging arbitrarily, and excommunicating all ſuch as wou'd not ſubſcribe to what the word of God had not determin'd; this juriſdiction, I ſay, fell before the moderation of Chriſt, that wou'd not condemn unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, becauſe his buſineſs was not to judge, but to ſave the world;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> they have one that ſhall judge them, ſaid our Saviour, making his word to be the ſole judge of controverſies. This arbitrary power uſurp'd over Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, could not maintain itſelf, when ſo plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by the Scripture in the Apoſtles behaviour, who had always refus'd it, referring the faithful to the word of God: The Idol fell before the Ark. The Scripture overthrows the authority the Miniſtry had aſſum'd; but us Miniſters being more cautious in this than the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins,</hi> who did not ſend away the Ark till after the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37429:8"/>of the Idol; the effects of their authority were felt, before any cou'd examine into the nature of it; the Shepherds Crook became a Scourge for all ſuch as wou'd not condeſcend to their decrees.</p>
            <p>Thus it was that the word of God loſt by degrees the priviledge of being the Rule of our Faith. 'Twas by this means the authority of the Scripture became tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to the ambition of the Miniſtry; and if ancient Philoſophers were given over to the luſt of their hearts, for having made the truth captive to injuſtice, ſo God exercis'd the ſame puniſhment upon the Miniſters of his Goſpel; they were given over to their own hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, for deviating from the rule Chriſt had ſet them, by which they ſhou'd have preſerv'd the purity of faith; By this deſire of the heart, I don't mean the ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous paſſions, that puniſh'd the pride of thoſe ancient Heathens: No, there is in mans heart a more refin'd and exalted deſire, he is ſtill more fond of, which is that he always had of being the Arbiter of his Religion: 'Twas to ſatisfy that deſire, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> made themſelves Gods. For this the <hi>Jews</hi> made themſelves a pleaſing idea of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> they expected; 'twas by this ſame deſire, which the <hi>Latin</hi> Miniſtry ſo blindly follow'd, that they begun to edify their Church by the authority of Chriſt, as Chriſt had edify'd his own by the Miniſtry of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Hence aroſe the worſhip of images, conniv'd at till then, as meer ornaments to Churches; hence was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd the uſe of <hi>Apotheoſis,</hi> by that pompous way of canonizing of Saints: Their Relicks were expos'd upon their Altars, their Indulgences were us'd to ſet off the ſolemnities deſign'd for them. What ſtrange alterations did Chriſt's Sacraments then receive? Nay, the very ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies the Apoſtles had us'd, were erected into Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and the Sacraments Chriſt had inſtituted were alter'd, either in their ſubſtance, or in their exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or part. No longer was the Supper of the Lord a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his body, but his very individual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: 'Twas no longer a memorial of his paſſion, but an expiatory Sacrifice. 'Twas no longer the uſe of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37429:9"/>ſubſtance, that was alter'd, but the very ſubſtance it ſelf. 'Twas no longer a deep veneration, and reſpect, due to the ſacred ſign of Chriſt's body, but a real adoration render'd to the Sacrament as to Chriſt himſelf. In a word, <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtianiz'd had the ſame fate with Pagan <hi>Rome,</hi> which loſt that Religion their Anceſtors profeſs'd, by having adopted that of all thoſe nations, they had a mind to bring under their power. Modern <hi>Rome</hi> had the misfortune to change the image of an incorruptible God into that of a corruptible man, and a ſpiritual and divine worſhip into a carnal and ſuperſtitious one.</p>
            <p>At the ſight of ſo amazing a revolution that occaſion'd ſuch woful diſtractions in the Church, I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear uſing the words of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> bewailing the lamentable condition of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.</note> How is the Gold become dim! How comes the doctrine of Chriſt, formerly ſo pure and ſo bright in the golden age of the Church, how comes it now to be wrapt up in the clouds of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? How is the fineſt gold chang'd? How is that Chriſtian piety, ſo lively, ſo ſublime of old, become now ſo lukewarm and ſo deſpicable? It formerly rais'd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hearts to Jeſus Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of the Father, but now it makes them ſtoop to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of him in the Sacrament of his body, which is but a means to convey his graces to us. How comes it to paſs that ſo pure a worſhip, whereof the ſole object was God, and Chriſt as Mediator, is now divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and the creatures? How are the precious ſons of <hi>Zion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> comparable to fine gold, eſteem'd as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the potter! How comes it to paſs that Chriſtians, who in the gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en days of the Church were lookt upon as ſo many Gods come down from Heaven, are now ſo much alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, how comes their Religion to be ſo earthly? They formerly carried Chriſt in their hearts; they expreſs'd theſe myſteries in every action of their lives, and now they think Chriſt can hardly be found but in Images of him; ſo frail, ſo corrupt is their piety, that they wou'd think themſelves without any Religion, were they once without their Images and Relicks, were they once depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37429:9"/>of the privledge of procuring themſelves Patrons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints. Whence comes ſo deplorable a change! Can we look upon the Church in this condition, as that new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw coming down from heaven, <hi>paepared as a Bride adored for her Husband;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revil.</hi> 21.2.</note> Alas! if it be the ſame <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> it ſhares in the ſame fate with that, whoſe ſad condition <hi>Jeremiah</hi> bewailed, and we may ſay with him, <hi>how doth the city ſit ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that was full of people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1</note> 
               <hi>How is ſhe become as a widow. She that was great among the Nations, and Princeſs among the Provinces, how is ſhe become tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary!</hi> Such was the fate of Chriſt's Church. It was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly full of worſhippers, who worſhipp'd in ſpirit and in truth; but after it was gone to decay, there were hardly ſeen any Chriſtians, but ſuch as were carnal, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous or ſuperſtitions. Chriſt her Spouſe had indeed promis'd to be with her till the end of the world, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſhe taught that Doctrine he had depoſited with her; but her Miniſters were backward in performing the conditions impos'd; they follow'd not ſo much the Scripture, as the interpretations they gave it, according to their particular intereſt and deſigns: therefore Chriſt abandon'd them. They preach'd the imaginations of their hearts, they ſet them forth as rules of faith, by means of that authority they uſurp'd over mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Hence came the deplorable ſtate of the Church, which was found inſenſibly burden'd with more precepts and ceremonies than the Synagogue; hence it was that the Church which had triumph'd over the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came herſelf tributary; in the flock, tributary to ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in the miniſtry, tributary to thoſe ſuperſtitions, which ignorance or ſlackneſs of piety had introduc'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the flock.</p>
            <p>You need not wonder at the ſtrangeneſs of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding; God ſuffer'd it to be ſo, the better to diſplay his incomprehenſible wiſdom. By permitting diſorder and corruption to invade the Church, occaſion'd by the pretended infallible authority the miniſtry had aſſum'd over the word of God: He wou'd make Chriſtianity ſenſible of the indiſpenſable neceſſity of ſubmitting the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37429:10"/>Miniſtry to his Holy Word, as he had order'd it. The Church is repreſented to us as terrible as an Army drawn up in battel array. For what makes an Army terrible to the enemy, but good order and diſcipline? What made the primitive Church ſo powerful and glorious? Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it was to the world, becauſe the truth and efficacy of its doctrine ſubmitted the fleſh to the ſpirit; terrible to Tyrants, becauſe it plac'd the pleaſures of this preſent life far belew the glorious advantages of a future ſtate; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came terrible to error, becauſe it ſubmitted reaſon to faith, tradition to revelation, the authority the Miniſtry has over the people, to the authority the word of God ought to have over the Miniſtry. God, ſaith St <hi>Paul,</hi> has ſet ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Paſtors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for the edifying of the Church, that the faithful might not be like Children toſs'd up and down with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wind of doctrine. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.</note>The Holy Ghoſt, ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, has ſet ſome overſeers to feed the Church of God, which he has purchas'd with his own blood. We own this ordination to be by God's appointment, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this Miniſtry upon that account; but the Miniſtry is of the nature of relative beings, it is not ſet up for it ſelf, the Miniſtry has a relation to God who eſtabliſh'd it; and for that reaſon, all that it teaches in Religion muſt be referr'd to the glory of God. Now, that relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does not appear, and is not made good, when that faith the Miniſtry would ſet up, has too great a relation to its own particular intereſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.</note> the Holy Ghoſt has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Overſeers and Paſtors to govern the Church of God; 'tis true their flock muſt liſten to them, in order to be inſtructed, but then they themſelves muſt liſten to the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 16.13, 14.</note> who ſpeaks by the word of God. When the ſpirit of truth is come, he will guide you into all truth; for he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf; but whatſoever he ſhall hear, that ſhall he ſpeak. He ſhall glorifie me, for he ſhall receive of mine, and ſhall ſhew it unto you. Here is, as it were, the finger of God pointing out the ſubordination of the Miniſtry to the Holy Ghoſt, who guides it; the Holy Ghoſt does not ſpeak of himſelf, he glorifies the Saviour that ſent him, by receiving from him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37429:10"/>what he teaches the Apoſtles. And muſt not this order laſt for ever? Is it poſſible there ſhou'd have been a time, when the Miniſtry had power to decide by its own authority, when it might be diſpenc'd from glorifying the Holy Ghoſt, by taking out of thoſe Sacred Writings he himſelf dictated, thoſe rules of faith it would impoſe upon the flock.</p>
            <p>If this ſubordination had laſted, if the Miniſtry had been in every particular rul'd by the word of God, wou'd the worſhip of Images have been ſet up, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly contradicted therein; wou'd not the hand of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias,</hi> that broke down the Brazen Serpent, whereby the people were led to Idolatry, have taken away under the Goſpel a worſhip, that proves ſo often a rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to Chriſtians? Wou'd not the Angel that took up the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> leſt divine honours ſhou'd be paid him, have hid the relicks of Saints in their Graves, rather than have permitted them to be carry'd in pomp about their Churches, and upon their Altars, there to receive ſuch honours and adorations as are only due to God? If the Goſpel had been conſulted, wou'd Chriſtians, that pretend to works of ſupererogation, be otherwiſe thought of than unprofitable Servants? Wou'd the Supper of the Lord have been taken for the real and ſubſtantial body of Chriſt, rather than for the virtue and efficacy thereof, if regard had been had to the ſtyle of the Goſpel, that always gives to the ſign the name of the thing ſignify'd, and oftentimes attributes to the effect the name of the cauſe that produces it. If Chriſt has edify'd his Church by himſelf, or his Apoſtles, how comes it that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel makes no particular mention of Tranſubſtantiation, of the Sacrifice, and worſhipping of the Sacrament? The firſt of theſe is a continual Miracle, the Sacrifice of the Altar is one of the eſſential parts of piety, the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Sacrament is ſuch, as muſt neceſſarily, if of divine inſtitution, make men that neglect it, guilty of the higheſt Profanation; but if forbid, of an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Idolatry. How comes the Goſpel to be ſo ſilent in this matter? Why did the Holy Ghoſt, who inſpir'd the Apoſtles with all the fundamental truths, conceal
<pb facs="tcp:37429:11"/>ſuch important ones from them? What! is God ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> diſpenſation, of the methods the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were to uſe in his worſhip, as to preſcribe the very leaſt ceremonies, nay the ſmalleſt veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels they ſhould uſe in their Sacrifices; and can it be thought under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, that Chriſt, who came to teach men how to worſhip in purity and in truth, and eſtabliſh a Religion far more excellent than that of the Law, ſhould have left it to tradition alone, to ſet rules for the moſt eſſential part of Chriſtian wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? The Church then is not of Chriſt's, not of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſetting up, thoſe that ſucceeded after the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Faith, are they that laid the foundation or Chriſtian Religion. But how does this appear proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Except the Lord build the houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.</note> they labour in vain that build it. Let them inſiſt never ſo much upon the antiquity, rank, and profound learning of their Doctors that taught theſe particular opinions; in Chriſt's Religion, there muſt be ſeen at leaſt Chriſt's hand in thoſe of the Goſpel Miniſters; that is, the will of Chriſt, and the doctrine of the Goſpel muſt be the foundation of faith and piety.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>All fleſh is as graſs,</hi> ſaith St <hi>Peter, and all the glory of man as the flower of graſs. The graſs withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away, but the word of the Lord endureth for ever. And this is the word which is preach'd unto you by the Goſpel.</hi> 'Tis that holy word which has always been the foundation of the Chriſtian faith; 'tis the only rule of faith in the Church of Chriſt. When Religion was upon its decline, tradition took place of the Goſpel, it became the foundation of faith, by means of the authority the Miniſtry had aſſum'd over the word of God; but when the purity of Chriſtianity was re-eſtabliſh'd, the word of God was reinſtated in all its prerogatives, which the Lord had given it over the Miniſtry; and it may be ſaid of the Reformation, what the Prophet ſaid of the eſtabliſhment of the Church; <hi>The ſame ſtone which the builders refus'd is become the head ſtone in the corner.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Lords doings and it is marvellous in our eyes. This is the day which the Lord has made: we will rejoyce and be glad in it.</hi> The autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37429:11"/>of the word of God, is undoubtedly that corner ſtone of the ſpiritual building, whereby you are reunited with the primitive Chriſtians, ſince you believe nothing but what they believ'd. 'Tis God Almighty himſelf that hath purify'd his Church, by reſtoring it to that order he had at firſt eſtabliſh'd. The Son of God being ſent into the world to enlighten all men, and the Holy Ghoſt which Chriſt ſent to his Apoſtles, have ſecretly reform'd in the Chriſtian Faith, all that was not eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the Goſpel. God has reſtored the purity of the Goſpel to its luſtre, and that ought to be the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your joy, ſince perſecution that attends it, ſerves to ſet off the glorious character of the Church of Chriſt, and that's the ſecond head of this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Balak</hi> thinks to compaſs his deſigns upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and rid himſelf more eaſily of them, if he can but get <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe them; he makes him look on all ſides; but the more he ſtrives to curſe them, the more he finds himſelf conſtrain'd to bleſs them. Thus the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tries all ways to render the Proteſtant Religion odious; they expoſe it in its Reformation, Reformers, Temper, and in its forſaking, as they pretend, the ancient Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. But as <hi>Balaam,</hi> with-held by the ſpirit of God, was proof againſt all the crafty contrivances of <hi>Balak,</hi> ſo a Chriſtian, who is enlighten'd by the Goſpel, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways look upon the Reformed Church, as <hi>Balaam</hi> did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Iſrael;</hi> 'tis <hi>a people that ſhall dwell alone, and ſhall not be reckoned among the Nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.</note> The Lord their God is with them, and the ſhout of a King is among them. In a word, he will cry out, notwithſtanding all worldly deſigns and Polices, <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and thy tabernacles, O Iſrael!</hi> This is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of a Chriſtian inlightned by the Spirit of God, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly convinc'd of the maxims of the Goſpel, and that thinks ſeriouſly on his Salvation; for among Chriſtians, who only bear the name of ſuch, and whoſe Religion is their Intereſt, there are many, who know the truth to be in that Church Chriſt has reviv'd; but ſome forſake it, becauſe 'tis forſaken in their native Country; others perſecute it, becauſe 'tis perſecuted by the world. But what matters it, if Religion be obſcure to worldly-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-men,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37429:12"/>who ſhut up their eyes to the truth, when they may be thereby expos'd to miſery and contempt? what matters it, if it be oppos'd by ſuch Chriſtians as find it their particular intereſt and advantage to be animated with a miſtaken zeal? 'twould be very unjuſt to judge of a Church by the opinion the world conceives of it; for whether we conſider the Church as expos'd to the contempt and reproaches the world ſtrives to over-cloud it with, or rais'd to luſtre and ſplendour, in ſpite of the world itſelf, thoſe very clouds are as bright and glorious, as that glittering light and purity it ſhines with in the eyes of true Chriſtians; and herein do we ſee the oracle of the Prophet <hi>David</hi> accompliſhed; there is a day that diſcovers to us another day, and a night that diſcovers to us another night. The beauty of the primitive Church, is a day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.3.</note> that diſcovers to us the excellency of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd Church; the motives of hatred and perſecutions, Chriſt and the primitive Church have undergone, form as it were a night, that diſcovers to us the principle of diſgraces and oppoſitions, that over-power the Church wherein Chriſt has renew'd the purity of Faith, which was in primitive Chriſtians. Who will not then admire the beauty of that reviv'd Church, ſo conſpicuous for its uniformity with the primitive Church? And who will forſake that Church, becauſe 'tis reviled by world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings? becauſe 'tis hated and perſecuted in ſome parts of the world, as Chriſt and the primitive Chriſtians were.</p>
            <p>This oppoſition the Church of Chriſt meets with in the world, is one of the faireſt ſtrokes to ſet off its beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; 'tis a Seal the Heavenly Father has ſealed it with, by a happy conformity with Chriſt. <hi>Behold this Child,</hi> ſaid <hi>Simeon, is ſet for the fall and riſing again of many in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and for a ſign which ſhall be ſpoken againſt.</hi> Would not one think,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he made a deſcription of the reformed Church, that having brought again Chriſtianity to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Faith, revives piety in ſome, and ſtirs up envy and animoſity in others, who make it the ſcope of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions. Let us conſider firſt the principle of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Church of Chriſt meets with in the world, and then we will examin the different objections raiſed againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37429:12"/>it, whereby it will appear, that all the methods the world takes to ſully and obſcure its glory, do but advance it to a higher degree.</p>
            <p>How comes it that reformation has always been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch hatred and contempt, that nothing has been left unpracticed in order to ſuppreſs it in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity? To find out the cauſe of this, we muſt ſearch into the principle of that hatred and envy the Synagogue and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> bore to Chriſt and his Church; and this is that night which diſcovers to us another night; what ſhall we do with this man, ſaid the Synagogue,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſpeaking of the Saviour of the world. This man does many miracles, if we let him thus alone, all men will believe on him.</p>
            <p>From this jealouſy which the Miniſters of the Law conceiv'd againſt him, aroſe that envy and implacable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred they bore him. He was no longer lookt upon but as a Seducer, who came with his new Doctrine to diſturb Peace and Religion. His miracles were attributed to the power of the Devil, and after that all endeavours us'd to cry him down in the minds of people, proved fruitleſs, his life was openly conſpired againſt, chuſing rather to ſacrifice him, and put him to death, than that the whole Nation (as they feared) ſhould periſh. What made Chriſtianity ſo odious to the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> nothing elſe but the pulling down of Images, and aboliſhing of ſuperſtitions, the world had been buried in for ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a time. The application is eaſy and plain: could that Religion which proteſted againſt the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty uſurp'd by the Miniſtry, have been reform'd, by taking the Scripture for the only rule of its Faith and Worſhip, without inforcing the Chriſtian world to the neceſſity of a reformation in thoſe Doctrines of the Church, and thoſe practical parts of Piety, which Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had not eſtabliſhed. It made the neceſſity of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation ſo apparent and manifeſt to the eyes of poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that thoſe Miniſters have made it their buſineſs to ſtifle the thoughts of it, both in themſelves and in their Flock. Hence it is, that they being highly offended, have omitted nothing in order to render this Church odious to the people, who were much more inclined to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37429:13"/>receive this impreſſion, becauſe Reformation ſeem'd to take away their Gods from them, by ſuppreſſing ſome acts of devotion, that made up the fundamental parts of their Piety. Hence part of Chriſtendom has been ſeen to conſpire the ruin of the Church Chriſt had re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, chuſing rather to ſacrifice it to an indiſcreet zeal, than that humane traditions, the uſe whereof ſo much flattered the corruption and pride of the heart, ſhou'd receive the leaſt prejudice. <hi>How goodly are thy Tents, O Jacob!</hi> How glorious it is for a Church which Chriſt has reviv'd, to be hated for the ſame reaſons, that made him odious to ſuch as would not receive his Faith! And how ſhameful it is for a Chriſtian Society to fall into the ſame blindneſs, and injuſtice of the Synagogue, by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to ſuppreſs a Church, for believing and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what the primitive Chriſtians believed!</p>
            <p>This is the principle of thoſe oppoſitions, which the reviv'd Church of Chriſt meets with in the World; their nature and progreſs will appear in thoſe, which Chriſt himſelf underwent here on earth; the Son of man ſhall be mock'd, ſcourg'd, and put to Death. 'Twas endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd at firſt to run down and ridicule Reformation, upon the account of newneſs imputed to its doctrine and Miniſtry; and when that wou'd not do, to diſcredit it in the minds of Chriſtians, 'twas attack'd with open force: Why did we murmur at it? 'Twas God permitted it ſo to be, to ſet off more gloriouſly the antiquity of the Church he has re-eſtabliſh'd, by that very novelty im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to it; 'tis God permits it to be aſſaulted with open force, the better to manifeſt the ſpirit and conſtancy of primitive Chriſtians. The Church Chriſt has reſtor'd, is not different from that he at firſt ſet up; 'tis the ſame myſtical body, form'd at one time, and reform'd in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But yet 'tis the ſame Church, and the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that wou'd make this uniformity to appear, gives Reformation the ſame fate, which his primitive Church had; it is loaded with reproaches, and oppreſs'd by a miſtaken Zeal of Religion, as the primitive Church was. But all the oppoſitions it meets with from the World, ſerve ſo much the more to increaſe its glory.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37429:13"/>
            <p>The Doctrine of Chriſt in the primitive Church was accuſed of novelty; the Miniſters of the Law objected the antiquity of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as the <hi>Latin</hi> Miniſtry objected to the Proteſtant Church, the antiquity of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The doctrine of Chriſt was indeed new, if compar'd with the traditions the Law was clogg'd with; but compar'd with the Law itſelf, the Goſpel was more ancient than. Tradition, whereof the antiquity was objected. Such is the newneſs wherewith they ſtrive to diſgrace the Reformation; 'tis new indeed, if compar'd with human traditions, which that Miniſtry makes part of the doctrine and worſhip of Chriſtian Religion; but, if compar'd with divine revelation, Reformation is as ancient as the Goſpel itſelf, which is the only rule of that faith and worſhip it profeſſes: and if the Apoſtle St <hi>Paul</hi> faith, that Jeſus Chriſt was yeſterday, to day, and for ever; we may reaſonably ſay that that Religion which leads Chriſtians by the authority of the Scripture, is the ſame which ſanctify'd thoſe that preceded the coming of the Meſſiah, thoſe that ſucceeded the eſtabliſhment of Evangelical faith, and will ſanctifie thoſe that ſhall be ſav'd till the end of all things. You are not then, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſeparated from the myſtical body of Chriſt, ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Covenant, as they wou'd impoſe upon you, ſince you profeſs a Religion founded only upon Holy, Writ, you are Citizens of the Holy City, Servants of the houſe of God, built upon the foundation of Prophets and Apoſtles, upon the Corner-ſtone, which is Jeſus Chriſt. That's the new doctrine you profeſs.</p>
            <p>But where was this Miniſtry before the Reformation? It was in the midſt of you, and you did not know it. The Evangelical Miniſtry was in the <hi>Latin</hi> one, which ſtill preſerv'd the fundamental points of Religion, tho it were already very much corrupted with traditional inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations. This Miniſtry impos'd upon Chriſtianity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that, notwithſtanding, it preach'd what Chriſt had taught in his Goſpel, yet it did not ſeem to act by the ſpirit of God, in that they thought their authority ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to alter Religion as they pleas'd; in this laſt reſpect they were faln away in the ſight of God, tho they ſtill
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37429:14"/>remain'd in their Apoſtolical functions in the ſight of men, giving them ſufficient food for their Salvation, ſo long as their hearts were at liberty to ſift the ore from the dreſs. An inſtance of this we have in the old law; <hi>Eli</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was caſt off in the ſight of God; the Prieſthood was transferr'd upon <hi>Samuel</hi>'s head; and yet <hi>Eli</hi> and his Children exercis'd the functions of it, till ſuch time as God had preſcrib'd <hi>Samuel</hi> to officiate in, who liv'd in the Temple, tho neither <hi>Eli</hi> nor the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple knew any thing of what God deſign'd him for. Thus he left the Scribes and Phariſees in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair. Thus he left the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops in the Chair of Orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and if he has preſerv'd the true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> under the Miniſtry of the Law, faithful Chriſtians under the <hi>Arian</hi> Miniſtry, may not he have preſerv'd the purity of Primitive Chriſtians under the corruption of the <hi>Roman</hi> Miniſtry? And if God permitted at laſt the diviſion of this Miniſtry, under which he had till then preſerv'd his Church, can any one doubt of the ſame individual Church being ſtill in one of thoſe two Miniſtries, that has reviv'd the purity of the Faith, which was in the primitive Chriſtians, without being drawn away by that Flood of human traditions, wherein Ambition, Intereſt, and Superſtition had a greater ſhare than Religion? Can any one doubt of Chriſt's Church's being in that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, whereof the particular character is the grounding of Chriſtian Faith and Worſhip, upon what Chriſt and his Apoſtles edify'd?</p>
            <p>If God ſuffer'd Chriſtianity for many ages to be bury'd in ignorance and ſuperſtition, 'twas a juſt puniſhment which he was willing to inflict upon an unfaithful Spouſe, whom he had in a manner left to herſelf, for deſpiſing his Laws. He had eſtabliſh'd his Church in the early days of Chriſtianity, after having left Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind a long time involv'd in the clouds of Idolatry and <hi>Jewiſh</hi> traditions; he re-eſtabliſh'd it once more, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the eyes of the Chriſtian World, to ſee the a buſes and vanities of human traditions, and made it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly ſhine forth like the Morning Sun, riſing all of a ſudden from the boſom of a diſmal night, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37429:14"/>ages of obſcurity had been forming; how great ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the corruption of Chriſtianity had been, yet the Gates of Hell did not prevail againſt it. But was it not enough for Almighty God to have preſerv'd a ſingle Spark of that ſacred Fire, that was almoſt extinguiſh'd upon the Altar of the Church? Was it not enough for him to have kept ſome hidden Fountain of that Water that ſprings forth into Life Eternal? But that great God who can give life and take it away as he pleaſes, who leads to the chambers of death, and is able to bring back, ſeem'd to have ſuffer'd the Gates of Hell to prevail a while againſt his Church, only to make that ſame Church more gloriouſly to triumph over them. He ſuffer'd it ſo to be, that the ſtrength of his arm might be as conſpicuous in the re-eſtabliſhing of his Church, as in the ſetting of it up. If the progreſs of Reformation be but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, which all of a ſudden open'd the eyes of the world to the vanities of human traditions; who can doubt, but that it was the hand of God alone, that wrought it? That the number of Goſpel-Miniſters has been ſeen to multiply, whilſt the Miniſtry was loaden with Riches, Honours, and Dignities, is not at all to be wondered at; the ſpirit of the world alone is ſufficient for that; but that the number of Goſpel-Miniſters has been ſeen to multiply, when the Miniſtry was deſtitute of temporal advantages; nay, when to deſire the Miniſtry, was to deſire an occaſion of Martyrdom, this is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Spirit of the World, 'tis the Spirit of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, who induces men to embrace ſuch a party. That the Chriſtian people have been ſeen wholly addicted to the practice of human Traditions and Superſtitions, is the conſequence of the corruption of ſo many ſucceſſive ages of ignorance; But that all of a ſudden part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has been ſeen to awake from a deep lethargy, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a worſhip wholly ſpiritual, deſtitute of all worldly pomp, cloſely purſu'd by envy and perſecution; in a word, to make up ſo numerous a Communion, tho it were by ſome accounted folly, and to others prov'd a ſhunbling block, ſure it muſt be the virtue of his ſpirit, and the efficacy of his word, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ound the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37429:15"/>of the new reviv'd Church, as it did that of the primitive one.</p>
            <p>Who can ſufficiently admire the conduct of divine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which has preſerv'd two Miniſtries, ſo directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, in the boſome of the ſame Church, as it former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſerv'd <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> in the ſame Temple: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who can chooſe but admire the wiſdom of God, in preſerving in the boſom of one and the ſame Church theſe two Miniſtrys, as it formerly preſerv'd <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> in the boſom of one common Mother? This is like the two Nations that ſhared the World between them. This is ſomething very nearly reſembling the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made between theſe two Brothers, wherein the transferring the Birth-right upon <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſtirs up in <hi>Eſau</hi> an implacable hatred againſt him. Herein appears the wiſdom of God, who having obſerv'd how the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church was faln into corruption in the midſt of Peace, expoſes the reviv'd Church to continual perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to keep up its purity, and diſtinguiſh the ſpirit that animates it, from the ſpirit of the Miniſtry that uſes all endeavours to oppreſs it.</p>
            <p>In the Communion of <hi>Rome,</hi> I obſerve a Miniſtry that baniſhes Chriſtians from the Church of Chriſt, meerly for being conformable to his word; a Miniſtry that uſes a temporal power to ſuppreſs Chriſtians, whoſe only crime conſiſts in preferring the Scripture before Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Is this the ſpirit of Chriſt, who made his word the ſole judge of controverſies? Is this the ſpirit of St <hi>Paul,</hi> who pronounces curſing againſt the Angels, and againſt himſelf, if he preach any thing but the Goſpel? Is this the ſpirit of St <hi>Peter,</hi> who meekly ſubmits to what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances and oppoſitions St <hi>Paul</hi> us'd againſt him? Or is it not rather generally indiſcreet zeal of the Apoſtles, when they wou'd have had fire to come down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, not knowing what Spirit they were of?</p>
            <p>Here I ſee Paſtors diſpers'd, faln Victims to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the oppoſite Miniſtry, who animated with the Spirit of St <hi>Paul,</hi> ſay after this great Apoſtle: You think your ſelves wiſe in Chriſt, and we are accounted as fools for the glory of Chriſt; you are ſtrong, and we are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37429:15"/>weak: You are in pomp and magnificence, and we, for preaching the Goſpel, are forc'd to wander up and down, expos'd to hunger, thirſt, and nakedneſs: You curſe us, and we return bleſſings: you excommunicate us, and we pray for you. Is it the ſpirit of the world that makes this Paſtor take up with ſo vile and deſpicable a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? No, that inſpires nothing but vanity; 'tis not the ſpirit of the fleſh, that inſpires nothing but ſoftneſs; 'tis not the ſpirit of the Devil, it breathes nothing but ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Now, Chriſtians, to which of theſe two Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrys, think ye, ſhall poſterity attribute the ſpirit of God to?</p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt, after having put the Paſtors to this trial, does not ſeem to have wholly abandon'd the flock to perſecution, to ſhew that his arm is not ſhorten'd, and that, notwithſtanding the corruption of the preſent age, the ſtrength and purity of faith had ſtill been preſerv'd in that very Communion, <hi>Rome</hi> made ſuch ſlight account of. 'Twas by faith <hi>Abraham</hi> left his Country, obeying the voice of God, tho he knew not whether he was to go. By that ſame faith it is this people have left their Country, to follow the voice of Chriſt, tho they knew not how divine providence ſhou'd diſpoſe of 'em: 'Twas by faith <hi>Abraham</hi> ſacrific'd his Son: 'Tis by faith that fathers expoſe their children to death, by the hazards they run in a long Voyage, rather than let their children imbibe ſo pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a doctrine: By faith <hi>Moſes</hi> preferr'd the reproaches of Chriſt before the pleaſures of a great Kings Court: By faith, ſo many perſons, as remarkable for their birth as their piety, have been willing to forgo their rank, eſtates, and hopes of advancement, to bear our Saviours Croſs, in all the hardſhips of a voluntary baniſhment. By and upon the account of Faith, ſo many Chriſtian Souls have ſuffer'd impriſonment, the Galleys, and ſubmitted to the rigour of a ſhameful death; they might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd their lives and liberty, but they would not, fully perſwaded they ſhall ſind a better in the Reſurrection, preferring the Croſs of Chriſt before the enjoyment of thoſe temporal advantages they muſt have bought with the price of their Religion; <hi>How goodly are thy Tents,
<pb facs="tcp:37429:16"/>O Jacob, and thy Tabernacles, O Iſrael.</hi> How glorious is it for Reformation to be at odds with the World, and yet ſo far above its reach, by Jeſus Chriſt, that encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages and fortifies it! But how ſhameful for thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who think they may do any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretence of extirpating Hereſy, to have caſt off the weapons of the Spirit, that St <hi>Paul</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, and to make uſe of an unheard of violence, which was but an occaſion for thoſe very Chriſtians <hi>Rome</hi> lookt upon as Hereticks, to ſpread the good odour of Chriſt and his Doctrine; among thoſe pretended He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, ſome knew how to dye for the Faith, tho they knew not how to diſpute concerning the Faith, others knew how to ſacrifice all to their Faith, becauſe they knew by the Goſpel, they had no other Country but Heaven, no prize but their Soul, nor any other treaſure but their Religion. Does not that Inviſible and Almighty hand, that bears up theſe ſufferers, by diſplaying in them the ſpirit and virtue of the primitive Chriſtians, make thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſenſible, they were in open war with God, when they thought they were only act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt rebellious children? Let them hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the buſhel, and expoſe upon the Candleſtick a Chriſtian Society, they in vain endeavour to ſuppreſs. Do not they, who ſo much boaſted of having triumph'd over the Reformation, perceive they bury their own Church under this pretended triumph? How can they think a Chriſtian and impartial poſterity will look upon their Religion as Chriſt's, ſo long as they fill the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world with ſo many thouſand barbarities they have us'd againſt them, contrary to the ſpirit of the Goſpel? Can they boaſt of having augmented the flock of Chriſt, with thoſe whom fear, intereſt, or hypocriſie hath forc'd into their Communion, and not their own choice? How ſhall they be able to juſtifie before God and men the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane, deſtribution of the Sacrament to ſo many timerous and unworthy Chriſtians, whom they know to have comply'd only with the time, and not with the truth?</p>
            <p>But laſtly, tho that Religion God ſo viſibly protects, ſhou'd ſtill be for a long time unknown to the Chriſtian
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37429:16"/>world, yet it will be never the leſs true: What matters it, if that myſterious fiery pillar that guides Gods people in the deſerts of this life be darkneſs to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> provided it give light to the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> tho the whoſe world ſhould conſpire the ruin of the Church, wherein Chriſt has reviv'd the purity of the faith, what can <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> fear, ſince they are under the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, that makes the blindneſs of mens hearts inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to the deſigns of his providence; and ſtops the current of mens paſſions when he pleaſes? <hi>Balak</hi> has no power over <hi>Balaam</hi>'s heart, becauſe God had ſuſpended his deſires; <hi>Balaam,</hi> tho never ſo ill affected, cou'd never curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe God had not curs'd him: and why ſhou'd you, Chriſtians, fear the World? If you are the bleſſed of God, not all mankind together can bring a curſe upon you: Wherefore Sanctify your ſelves in that ſtate, his providence has plac'd you in: omit nothing, in order to be a holy people, conſecrated to the Lord; that ſame God, who made <hi>Balaam</hi> bleſs <hi>Iſrael,</hi> may one day force bleſſings from thoſe very perſons, that now curſe you; the Arm of the Lord is not ſhorten'd. He is able to make your faith to Triumph; and have you not many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this already, who daily ſee Proſelytes come among you, converted to the Faith, by having oppos'd the Faith; the very enemies of your Religon become the Profeſſors and Aſſertors of it; how unſpeakable a joy it is! What comfort for a Church, to derive ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a fertility from that ſtate fleſh and blood lookt upon as in its laſt agony, There is but one ſimple thing, Chriſtians, can ſtop the bleſſings God ſo abundantly ſhowers upon your Church, which is the being unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to your vocation. 'Tis not you properly, who made God your choice, by forſaking all for the faith; 'tis God himſelf has made choice of you in the Chriſtian World, to maintain the glory of his name, and diſplay the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſtianity in your Communion; but alas! how deplorable wou'd it be, if after having begun with the Spirit, you ſhou'd now think of ending with the fleſh! How ſad a thing wou'd it be, if your heart, liſtening to the ſuggeſtions of nature, ſhou'd be led away towards
<pb facs="tcp:37429:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37429:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:37429:18"/>that Earthly Country, you have once ſacrificed to your faith! St <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, thoſe ancient Patriarchs I mention'd to you, dwelt very contendedly under Tents, notwithſtanding the hardſhips attending that condition; opportunities of returning into their Country were not wanting; but their minds did not run that way, becauſe they deſired a far better, that is a heavenly one; therefore God was not aſham'd to be call'd their God. You have indeed opportunities, and are at liberty to return into your Country; but is there any thing can poſſibly tempt you; your dear <hi>Zion</hi> lies in the duſt; the ways of <hi>Zion</hi> do mourn, her her Prieſts ſigh, her Virgins are affliected, and ſhe is in bittenrneſs; wou'd your hearts now be leſs mov'd at this deplorable ſight, which your eyes formerly could not bear? Cou'd you be ſo bold as to tempt the Lord, after you have been convine'd of your weakneſs by your flight? cou'd you promiſe your ſelves, he wou'd ſupport you in thoſe danges your ſlackneſs of piety wou'd expoſe you to? ſo many thouſand Chriſtians, who long to be in the ſame happy circumſtances with you, are now engag'd with the enemies of your Salvation and theirs. Why wou'd you damp their courage by your inconſtancy; <hi>Iſrael</hi> is fighting with <hi>Amaleck;</hi> let us endeavour to lift up pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled hands to Heaven, to bring down upon him bleſſings from above. A Chriſtian Life is nothing but a Pilgrimage; there is no place upon earth, proves a baniſhment to him; Heaven is the only Country we ought to long after; purity of Faith and the liberty of profeſſing it, is the moſt ſolid, and only hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs a Chriſtian can meet with in this World; cou'd you be forgerful of that exceſſive love, where with Chriſt has ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favour'd you? And who of us, ought not out of a deep ſenſe for ſo ſingular a favour, cry out with the Apoſtle, who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſs, or famine, or perſecution, or nakedneſs? No ſure, in all theſe calamities the elect always remain victorious through the aſſiſtance of him that loveth them. If the Lord be my light, if the Lord be my ſtrength, I may boldly ſay, I am ſure neither life, nor death, nor things preſent, nor things to come ſhall ever ſeparate me from the love, which is in Chriſt Jeſus. One day within the Courts of his Church is better than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in the Tents of the ungodly. What can ſhake my faith in a Church. where of Chriſt is the foundation, the maſter-builder, and the head? Has the World any thing that can ſtrike me with terror, whilſt I am in a Church, wherein Chriſt turns all to the glory of his Children, and confuſion of his enemies? Chriſt is gain to me, whether I live or dye. But I ſhall not dye; I am certain I ſhall live to ſing the infinite mercies of that Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who having made known to me the beauty of <hi>Iſrae</hi> upon earth, ſhall through his mercy introduce me into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> to which place God of his great mercy bring us all for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom with</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37429:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
